Eugen Teuber Papers 1910-1994 1912-1914 Mss.Ms.Coll.57
American Philosophical Society
Eugen Teuber Papers
Bulk, 1912-1914
1910-1994
Mss.Ms.Coll.57
American Philosophical Society
0.5 Linear feet
As a young graduate student at the University of Berlin in 1912, Eugen Teuber (1889-1958) was hired to help establish the Anthropoiden Station auf Teneriffa (Tenerife Primate Station) for the Prussian Academy of Sciences, the first field station devoted to behavioral research on primates. As its first director, Teuber played a crucial role in setting up the facilities and acclimating the chimpanzees to their new environment, and he was a co-participant in the first trials of Wolfgang Köhler's famous experiments to evaluate the intelligence of apes. The papers of Eugen Teuber document the founding and earliest years of the Anthropoiden Station auf Teneriffa. A small (0.5 linear feet), tightly focused collection, it contains a series of official documents relating to the establishment of the Station, approximately 20 letters between Teuber and officials in Berlin, including Wilhelm Waldeyer and Max Rothmann, some research notes, and over 100 photographs of the chimpanzees and facilities. The collection includes Teuber's notes on the first trial of Wolfgang Köhler's famous "fruit basket" experiment in December 1913.
Teuber, Eugen,1889-1958.
Bibliography
Teuber, Marianne L., "The founding of the primate station, Tenerife, Canary Islands," American Journal of Psychology 107 (1994): 551-581.
Related Archival Materials note
The APS also houses the papers of Wolgang Koehler, Teuber's successor at the Tenerife Primate Station.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Gift of Marianne L. Teuber, 1988.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of Eugen Teuber document the founding and earliest years of the Anthropoiden Station auf Teneriffa (Tenerife Primate Station), the pioneering research station established by the Prussian Academy of Sciences in 1912. A small (0.5 linear feet), tightly focused collection, it contains a series of official documents relating to the establishment of the Station, approximately 20 letters between Teuber and officials in Berlin, including Wilhelm Waldeyer and Max Rothmann, some research notes, and over 100 photographs of the chimpanzees and facilities. The collection includes Teuber's notes on the first trial of Wolfgang Köhler's famous "fruit basket" experiment in December 1913.
The visual documentation in the collection is outstanding, with 58 different images (97 developing-out or printing-out prints, 5 lantern slides, and 22 negatives) depicting Teuber, the chimpanzees, and the Station itself. These provide a good sense of the physical appearance of the ape quarters, and hint at some of Teuber's research priorities, with several views of chimps standing upright, socializing, or reaching for treats of cocoa or other foods. The collection also includes a draft and published version of a paper written by Teuber's daughter-in-law, Marianne L. Teuber, "The Founding of the Primate Station, Tenerife, Canary Islands" (1994).
Biographical/Historical note
As a young graduate student at the University of Berlin in 1912, Eugen Teuber (1889-1958) was hired to help establish the Anthropoiden Station auf Teneriffa (Tenerife Primate Station) for the Prussian Academy of Sciences, the first field station devoted to behavioral research on primates. As its first director, Teuber played a crucial role in setting up the facilities and acclimating the chimpanzees to their new environment, and he was a co-participant in the first trials of Wolfgang Köhler's famous experiments to evaluate the intelligence of apes.
Born and raised in Berlin, Teuber was educated at the Collège Français before entering the University of Leipzig to study under Wilhelm Wundt. Influenced by Wundt's psychology, Teuber enrolled at the University of Berlin to pursue a doctorate. In the midst of his studies, the neurophysiologist Max Rothmann proposed establishing a research station under the auspices of the Prussian Academy of Sciences not only as a means of supplying experimental animals for neuroanatomical research, but as a place to study the behavior of higher primates in an environment relatively similar to their natural habitat. Although his first request for support in 1910 was declined, Rothmann persevered and obtained approval his station on reapplication in 1912, securing funding from both the Academy and from private sources, including the Plaut and Selenka Foundations and the recently-established Albert Samson Foundation, chaired by the eminent anatomist Wilhelm Waldeyer. The difficulties of working on mainland Africa persuaded Rothmann to locate his facilities in the Canary Islands, comparatively near the German colony of Cameroon (a source for his experimental subjects).
At the suggestion of the psychologist Carl Stumpf from the Academy, Rothmann considered the young Wolfgang Köhler, Max Wertheimer, and David Katz for the position of director at the Station, but he initially favored Oskar Pfungst, the experimental psychologist known for his work debunking Kluge Hans, the calculating horse. In November 1912, however, Pfungst declined the position, and with the first shipments of chimpanzees slated to arrive soon at Tenerife -- some having already been held in captivity for several months -- the need for a replacement became critical. Under the circumstances, Waldeyer suggested that Eugen Teuber, then only 23, might be suitable for the position, and despite Stumpf's reservations about Teuber's inexperience in animal psychology, Teuber agreed to a one year contract on Dec. 17, 1912.
On Januayr 8, 1913, Teuber and his wife Rose (who also acted as assistant) landed at Tenerife, carrying with them a set of architectural plans for the new facility. Drawn in Berlin by the architect Erich Levy, but never implemented, the plans would have resulted in a building that more resembled a Schwartzwald chalet than a research station, however other needs more pressing than construction soon took precedence. Discovering that the seven chimps who had recently arrived (Sultan, Rana, Chica, Grande, Konsul, Tercera, and Tchego) were suffering from colds, and that one had died, Teuber moved quickly to improve their conditions and nurse them back to health. A ordered the construction of a large, open-air pen enclosed by high netting in which the apes could run about, while work proceeded on an ape house with four sleeping chambers and a long runway for exercise. Although it was small, the attached laboratory had up to date facilities for photography and sound recording.
Although much of Teuber's time was occupied with the details of care and feeding of the animals and construction of the station itself, Teuber also engaged in observations on chimpanzee behavior and, at the suggestion of Rothmann, he took notes their physical development. Teuber was particularly interested in the spontaneous behaviors exhibited the young male, Sultan, who often took the lead in their boisterous play, but he also made important observations on chimp communication and emotional expression, including vocalizations, facial expressions, gestures, and "dances." Using both the camera and sound recordings to document his work, Teuber concluded that chimp vocalizations were expressions of affect rather than a true language, though at one point, he considered the possibility that chimps might be able to learn sign language (likely, he thought), and he and Rothmann considered whether chimps could be taught to recognize vocal or visual signs as representatives of "certain objects," such as foods (not probable).
When Rothmann toured the station in August 1913, he found things in excellent order and reported positively on the health of the animals, the state of the buildings, and Teuber's diligent care. When Köhler arrived in December 1913 to take over control of the Station, the laboratory was already fully functional. Under Köhler, the priorities of research at the station shifted dramatically, moving away from the project of finding a substitute for language to performing "language-free" experiments of goal-oriented behavior to reveal "insight" or thought. Teuber and his wife remained in Tenerife for a few weeks to help Köhler find his bearings and to ease the transition for the chimpanzees, and they were co-participants in the first version of Köhler's famous fruit basket experiment on Dec. 31, 1913, the first conclusive demonstration of ape intelligence.
The Teubers left for Berlin in mid-January 1914, only ten months before the start of the First World War. During the war Eugen Teuber served as a communications officer on the Eastern front, after which he completed his doctorate in philosophy at the University of Rostock in 1921 with a dissertation on the artistic philosophy of Jean-Baptiste Dubos. Rather than entering academia, however, Teuber signed on as scientific director for Adrema, a business machine company. He was transferred to Denmark in 1938 to serve as director of exports, and he and his wife both became Danish citizens.
Köhler remained at the Anthropoiden Station throughout the War, but when the owner of the property on which the Station was located sold out to a British firm in 1918, Köhler was forced to relocate. The Station closed permanently in October 1920, five months after Köhler returned to Germany to become Director of the Psychological Institute at the University of Berlin.
Anthropoiden Station auf Teneriffa; Köhler, Wolfgang,1887-1967.; Waldeyer-Hartz, Wilhelm von, 1836-1921; Animal psychology.; Chimpanzees.; Lantern slides; Photographs; Primatology
- Eugen Teuber Papers, 1910-1994; 0.5 linear feet (Box 1)
  - Betrachtungen uber den dermaligen Stand des Krallissmus, 1914; Pr. Ms (incomplete), pp.3-28; Dexler, H.
    Scope and Contents note
    On Clever Hans (Kluge Hans)
  - In Memoriam Otto Rothmann, 1914; Silk ribbon
    Printed memorial silk ribbon for Otto Rothmann (son of Max Rothmann) killed in the war.
  - Records, 1914; 3 folders; Tenerife Primate Station.
    - Arbeitsplan, 1913; TMs, 2p.; Tenerife Primate Station. (Folder 1)
      Program of observations to be made o the chimpanzees.
    - Der Kaufpreis för Land..., 1913 Jan. 22; TMs, 2p.; Tenerife Primate Station. (Folder 1)
    - Die Untersuchung der Chimpansen, 1913; TMs, 4p.; Tenerife Primate Station. (Folder 1)
      Program of observations to be made o the chimpanzees, with marginal notes by Teuber.
    - Vertrag [with Eugen Teuber], 1913; TD, 3p.; Tenerife Primate Station. (Folder 1)
    - Accounts, 1913-1914; 8 items; Tenerife Primate Station. (Folder 2)
      Accounts periodically submitted for building materials, fruit, cocoa, bread, and rice for the animals; straw and blankets; apparatus; motion picture camera; phonograph; stopwatch; salaries for the caretaker and construction worker.
    - Miscellaneous records, 1913; 4 items; Tenerife Primate Station. (Folder 3)
      Includes Verzeichnes der Böcher der Anthropoiden-Station and 3 items on construction of pens for the primates
  - Blueprints, 1913; 1 item; Tenerife Primate Station [Erich Levy]
    Elevation and floorplan for scientific laboratories drawn by Erich Levy, Berlin.
    - Agreement with Eugen Teuber, 1912 Dec. 20; TDS, 1p. (5 copies); Levy, Erich
      Agreement with architect
  - Correspondence, 1912; 2 items; Teuber, Eugen
    - To Eugen Teuber, 1912 Dec. 8; ALS, 1p.; Waldeyer, Wilhelm
    - To Eugen Teuber, 1912 Dec. 12; TLS, 1p.; Russak, Hugo
  - Correspondence, 1913; 10 items; Teuber, Eugen
    - To Wilhelm Waldeyer?, 1913 Feb. 8; ALS, 4p. (inc.); Teuber, Eugen
    - To Eugen Teuber, 1913 Feb. 11; TLS, 1p.; Waldeyer, Wilhelm
      "Cimpanzee corpse" prepared by George Perez has arrived in good condition at the Anatomical Institute.
    - To Eugen Teuber, 1913 May 6; ALS, 1p.; Waldeyer, Wilhelm
    - To Wilhelm Waldeyer?, 1913 Apr. 1; ALS, 3p. (inc.); Teuber, Eugen
    - To Eugen Teuber, 1913 May 15; ALS, 7p.; Rothmann, Max
    - To Eugen Teuber, 1913 June 17; ALS, 3p.; Waldeyer, Wilhelm
    - To Eugen Teuber, 1913 July 4(?); Tgm, 1p.; Lander
    - To Eugen Teuber, 1913 Nov. 26; ALS, 4p.; Waldeyer, Wilhelm
    - To Eugen Teuber, 1913 Dec. 15; TLS, 2p.; Ahlers, Jakob
      German Consul regarding travel arrangements for return trip to Germany for the Teubers.
    - To Eugen Teuber, 1913 Dec. 17; ALS, 2p.; Waldeyer, Wilhelm
  - Correspondence, 1914; 4 items; Teuber, Eugen
    - To Eugen Teuber, 1914 Feb. 1; ALS, 2p.; Waldeyer, Wilhelm
      Acknowledges Teuber's gift of books and inquires about what Köhler might need. Mentions that Teuber has been praised by Köhler for his outstanding and exemplary administration of the Station (see also the letter May 11, 1914).
    - To Herr Hertzer, 1914 Mar. 12; ALS, 2p. (inc.); Teuber, Eugen
    - To Eugen Teuber, 1914 May 11; TLS, 1p.; Waldeyer, Wilhelm
    - To Eugen Teuber, 1914 May 12; ALS, 1p.; Waldeyer, Wilhelm
  - Correspondence, 4 items; Teuber, Eugen
  - Photographs, Folder 1, 1913; 6 items; Teuber, Eugen
    - Teuber and chimpanzee Terzera, 1913; 6 copies; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 1)
  - Photographs, Folder 2, 1913; Teuber, Eugen
    - "Chimpanzee walking upright" [reaching for cocoa], 1913; 4 copies; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 2:1a-b)
    - "Chimpanzee walking upright" [reversed], 1913; 2 copies; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 2:1c)
    - Chimpanzee walking upright, 1913; 1 print; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 2:1d)
    - Chimpanzee walking upright, 1913; 4 copies; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 2:2a-b)
    - Chimpanzee reaching for food, 1913; 4 copies; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 2:2c-d)
  - Photographs, Folder 3, 1913; Teuber, Eugen
    - Two chimpanzees standing, 1913; 1 print; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 3:1a)
    - Two chimpanzees standing, 1913; 1 print; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 3:1b)
    - Chimpanzee reaching for food, 1913; 1 print; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 3:1c)
    - Chimpanzee with arm extended, begging for cocoa, 1913; 1 print; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 3:1d)
    - Chimpanzee standing, 1913; 1 print; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 3:2a)
    - Chimpanzee standing, arm extended, 1913; 2 prints; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 3:2b)
    - Chimpanzee reaching into open window, 1913; 3 prints; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 3:2c)
    - Chimpanzee standing upright, 1913; 1 print; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 3:2d)
  - Photographs, Folder 4, 1913; Teuber, Eugen
    - Young chimpanzee standing, arm extended, 1913; 1 print; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 4:1a)
    - Young chimpanzee standing, arm extended, 1913; 1 print; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 4:1b)
    - Young chimpanzee standing, arm extended, 1913; 1 print; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 4:1c)
    - Two chimpanzee swinging on pole, 1913; 2 prints; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 4:1d)
    - Close-up of chimpanzee, 1913; 7 prints; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 4:2a-d)
  - Photographs, Folder 5, 1913; Teuber, Eugen
    - Chimpanzee standing, arm extended, 1913; 3 prints; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 5:1a-b)
    - Chimpanzee in motion, 1913; 1 print; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 5:1c)
    - Chimpanzee looking out window, 1913; 1 print; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 5:1d)
    - Close-up of chimpanzee, 1913; 1 print; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 5:2a)
    - Close-up of chimpanzee in cage chin held up, 1913; 1 print; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 5:2b)
    - Teuber holding chimpanzee, 1913; 1 print; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 5:2c)
    - Underside of chimpanzee foot, 1913; 1 print; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 5:2d)
      See 11c.
  - Photographs, Folder 6, 1913; Teuber, Eugen
    - Chimpanzees on a ladder, 1913; 7 prints; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 6:1a-d)
    - Chimpanzees destroying the banana tree, 1913; 1 print; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 6:2a)
    - Sultan, below, Rana in top, trying to destroy a banana tree, 1913 May; 1 print; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 6:2b)
    - Chimpanzee walking on knuckles, 1913; 1 print; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 6:2c)
  - Photographs, Folder 7, 1913; Teuber, Eugen
    - Three chimpanzees in cage, 1913; 1 print; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 7:1a)
    - Three chimpanzees in cage, 1913; 1 print; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 7:1b)
    - Three chimpanzees in open pen, 1913; 3 prints; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 7:1c-d)
    - Two chimpanzees in open air runway by pens, 1913; 1 print; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 7:2a)
    - Chimpanzee sitting on crate in open air runway by pens, 1913; 1 print; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 7:2b)
    - Two chimpanzees in open air runway by pens, 1913; 3 prints; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 7:2c-d)
  - Photographs, Folder 8, 1913; Teuber, Eugen
    - Man holding young chimpanzee by the arms, 1913; 1 print; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 8:1a)
    - Man standing next to young chimpanzee, 1913; 1 print; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 8:1b)
    - Chimpanzees by their pens, 1913; 1 print; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 8:1c)
    - Chimpanzee at food troughs, 1913; 1 print; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 8:1d)
    - Teuber with young chimpanzee in pen, 1913; 2 prints; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 8:2a)
    - Teuber with young chimpanzee in open air runway, 1913; 1 print; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 8:2b)
      See 11a.
    - Teuber with two young chimpanzees, 1913; 1 print; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 8:2c)
  - Photographs, Folder 9, 1913; Teuber, Eugen
    - Two chimpanzees in cage, 1913; 1 print; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 9:1a)
    - Two chimpanzees in cage, 1913; 1 print; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 9:1b)
    - Chimpanzees in cage, 1913; 2 prints; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 9:1c)
    - Chimpanzee in cage, 1913; 1 print; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 9:1d)
    - Teuber with chimpanzee in cage, 1913; 1 print; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 9:2a)
    - Teuber with chimpanzee in cage, 1913; 1 print; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 9:2b)
    - Chimpanzee in cage, 1913; 1 print; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 9:2c)
    - Teuber with chimpanzee in cage, 1913; 1 print; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 9:2d)
  - Photographs, Folder 10, 1913; Teuber, Eugen
    - Young chimpanzee on crate, 1913; 1 print; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 10a)
    - Teuber with two chimpanzees, 1913; 1 print; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 10b)
    - Portrait of two women [proof], 1913; 1 print; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 10c)
  - Photographs, Folder 11, 1913; Teuber, Eugen
    Folder 11 includes the highest quality selection of prints that are duplicated elsewhere.
    - Eugen Teuber with Tchego, 1913; 1 print; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 11a)
    - In the runway of the primate house, 1913; 1 print; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 11b)
      See also 7.2c.
    - Chimpanzee foot, 1913; 1 print; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 11c)
    - Chimpanzee walking upright, 1913; 1 print; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 11)
      See also 2.1c
    - Chimpanzees on ladder, 1913; 1 print; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 11e)
      See also 6.1a.
    - In the runway of the primate house, 1913; 2 prints; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 11)
      See also 3.2c
    - Rose and Eugen Teuber with Consul, caretaker in background, 1913; 1 print; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 11g)
  - Photographs (negatives), 1913; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 12)
  - Photographs (glass plates and lantern slides), 1913; Teuber, Eugen
    - Chimp (Sultan) with arm extended, begging for cocoa, 1913; Lantern slide; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 13)
    - Anthropoiden Station, 1913; Lantern slide; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 14)
    - Chimp (Sultan) with arm extended, 1913; Lantern slide; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 15)
    - Teuber with two chimpanzees (slide broken), 1913; Lantern slide; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 16)
    - Chimpanzee sitting on crate in runway, 1913; Lantern slide; Teuber, Eugen (Folder 17)
  - Research notes: Intelligenz Handlungen, 1913 Dec. 31; AMs, 5p.; Teuber, Eugen
    Köhler's fruit basket experiment, including observations on chimp Sultan.
  - Research notes: Missie, 1913; AMs, 8p.; Teuber, Eugen
    Observations on chimp Missie (Perhaps formerly called Tercera).
  - Research notes: Über Nachahmung, 1913; AMs, 2p.; Teuber, Eugen
    Introductory remarks on imitation
  - Misc. notes, 1913-1914; 15 items; Teuber, Eugen
  - The founding of the Primate Station, Tenerife, Canary Islands, 1988; TMs, 29p.; Teuber, Marianne L.
    Final draft
  - The founding of the Primate Station, Tenerife, Canary Islands, 1994; Pr. Ms., 30p. (2 copies); Teuber, Marianne L.
    Published in American Journal of Psychology 107 (1994): 551-581
  - Magazines: La Alhambra, 1910; 1 item
    Issue of La Alhambra 13, 303 (1910)
  - Magazines: Berliner Tageblatt, 1913 Aug. 9; 1 item
  - Magazines: Die Gartenlaube, 1911
    Misc. issues